Guide to the Montana Livestock Sanitary Board Records 1907-1967
Montana Historical Society
1907-1967
RS 61
Montana Livestock Sanitary Board Records
9 linear feet of shelf space
These Montana Livestock Sanitary Board records (1907-1967) consist of correspondence, financial records, legal documents, reports, subject files, and miscellany for the Board, plus subgroups on foot-and-mouth disease, and tuberculosis. (Artifacts, maps, printed material, and photographs have been transferred to the Museum, Library, and Photograph Archives respectively.)
The Montana Live Stock Sanitary Board was established in 19O7 and consisted of three members: the president of the Board of Stock Commissioners, the president of the Board of Sheep Commissioners, and the president of the State Board of Health. The State Veterinarian served as secretary and executive officer of the Board. The Board was empowered to govern quarantines, establish and maintain livestock sanitary regulations, direct and regulate the slaughter of all diseased animals, provide for meat inspection, and provide for the payment of indemnity when required.
In 1921 the legislature increased the size of the Board to include all six members of the Livestock Commission, with the chairman of the Commission serving as chairman of the Board. The Board was also given additional powers, including the power to regulate the importation of livestock, the eradication and control of livestock diseases, and the movement and quarantine of animals infected with contagious diseases within the state. Additional powers were gradually granted by succeeding legislatures. In 1931 the Board got the power to inspect and grade meat; in 1949 the Board assumed the regulation of Montana's rendering plants; and in 1953 the Board began the supervision of garbage feeders and artificial inseminators.
The Montana Veterinary Research Laboratory, at Montana State College in Bozeman, was organized in 1929, as a cooperative effort of the Montana Livestock Sanitary Board, the Montana Experiment Station, the Montana Stockgrowers Association, and the Montana Woolgrowers Association. The laboratory was established to investigate diseases of range cattle and sheep.
Dr. William J. Butler was appointed state veterinary surgeon on March 4, 1913. He resigned in 1948 and was followed by Dr. Howard F. Wilkins (1948-1954) and Dr. Hadleigh Marsh (1954-1956). In 1956 Dr. J.W. Safford became state veterinarian and served until 1973.
The Montana Live Stock Sanitary Board was abolished in 1971, and its functions were transferred to the newly created Board of Livestock, which vested these responsibilities in the Department of Livestock, Animal Health Division, headed by the State Veterinarian.
The Montana Livestock Sanitary Board Records consist of general records from the Board, as well as records specific to two distinct programs overseen by the Board. The collection has been organized into four subgroups; three representing the records of the Board and its programs, and the fourth a listing of any items transferred to another program within the Montana Historical Society.
The Montana Live Stock Sanitary Board subgroup contains interoffice correspondence (1911-1922, 1957-1959) between the state veterinarian and other administrative officials and the field veterinarians around the state; general correspondence (1911-1922, 1956-1959) arranged into Montana correspondence, out-of-state correspondence, and topical correspondence; and outgoing circular letters (1913-1915, 1925-1929, 1957). This subgroup also includes financial records (1917-1968); legal documents (1922-1937); legislative materials (1957-1959); minutes of the Board (1956-1959); press releases (1959); annual reports (1919-1928); weekly field reports (1915-1918) of assistant state veterinarians; speeches and writings (1956-1959) of Dr. J.W. Safford and other Board employees; a subject file (1921-1961) on Bang's Disease, the State Laboratory Building Commission, and other topics; miscellany; and clippings.
The Foot-and-Mouth Disease subgroup contains general correspondence (1914-1915) documenting the successful efforts of the Board to combat the 1914 epidemic of this disease in Montana. The largest number of letters are with ranchers and homesteaders hoping to bring cattle and horses into the state and inquiring about quarantine regulations.
The Tuberculosis subgroup documents the Board's Tuberculosis Control Program during the 193Os. Earlier efforts to control this disease are partially documented in the general correspondence of the Montana Live Stock Sanitary Board subgroup. This subgroup contains general correspondence, legal documents, reports, and miscellany.
The Separations subgroup contains a list of the artifacts, maps, printed material, and photographs which have been transferred to the Museum, Library Map Collection, Library, and Photograph Archives respectively.
The collection is arranged by subgroup and then by series.
Collection open for research.
Acquisition information is available upon request.
This collection is indexed under the following headings in the Montana Historical Society Archives catalog. Researchers desiring materials about related topics, persons, or places should search under these terms.
Agriculture and state; Cattle--Diseases; Coyotes; Dairying; Foot-and-mouth disease; Horses--Diseases; Predatory animals--Control; Sheep ranches--Montana; Swine--Breeding; Veterinarians--Montana; Veterinary hygiene; Veterinary medicine
St. Ignatius (Mont.); Wyoming
Montana; Agriculture; Government and Politics; Fisheries and Wildlife; Medicine and Health
Detailed Description of the Collection
The following section contains a detailed listing of the materials in the collection
- Montana Livestock Sanitary Board
  - Interoffice Correspondence
    - Dr. Glenn R. Bach (Medicine Lake), 1914-1915 (Box-folder 1 / 1)
    - Dr. John C. Boyd (Kalispell), 1912-1915 (Box-folder 1 / 2)
    - Dr. Z.C. Boyd (Butte, Chinook), 1911-1914 (Box-folder 1 / 3)
    - Dr. A.J. Butterfield (Great Falls), 1911 (Box-folder 1 / 4)
    - Dr. A.H. Cheney (Miles City, Polson), 1910-1915 (Box-folder 1 / 5-7)
    - Dr. A.J. Du Frene (Glendive, Ekalaka), 1911-1916 (Box-folder 1 / 8-10)
    - Dr. F.S. Gray (Billings, Lewistown, Red Lodge, Terry, Miles City), 1911-1916 (Box-folder 1 / 11-14)
    - Dr. S.F. Griesemer (Huntley, Powderville), 1913-1915 (Box-folder 1 / 15)
    - Dr. C.A. Hatterscheid (Billings, Culbertson), 1913-1915 (Box-folder 1 / 16)
    - Dr. O.J. Johnson (Miles City), 1912-1915 (Box-folder 1 / 17)
    - Dr. A.D. Knowles (Livingston) (also includes his correspondence as Secretary-Treasurer of the Montana Veterinary Medical Association, a report on glanders in Yellowstone National Park, 1911, and article on treatment of lupine weed poison in horses, 1916), 1911-1916 (Box-folder 1 / 18-19)
    - Dr. M.H. Kuhl (Missoula), 1913-1915 (Box-folder 1 / 20)
    - Dr. Malcolm McFarlane (Billings, Great Falls), 1914-1915 (Box-folder 1 / 21)
    - Dr. Jonathan J. Mitchell (Butte, Anaconda, Missoula, Great Falls), 1914-1916 (Box-folder 1 / 22)
    - Dr. A.C. Morrow (Dillon) (includes report on hog cholera in Dillon, 1914), 1911-1915 (Box-folder 1 / 23)
    - Dr. E.D. Nash (Helena), 1914-1915 (Box-folder 1 / 24)
    - Dr. W.C. Orr (Dillon), 1911-1915 (Box-folder 1 / 25)
    - Dr. J.W. Richardson (Malta), 1914-1916 (Box-folder 1 / 26)
    - Dr. C.H. Stevens (Stevensville, Missoula), 1911-1915 (Box-folder 1 / 27-28)
    - Dr. Walter Taylor (Bozeman), 1912 (Box-folder 1 / 29)
    - Dr. Howard Welch (Bozeman) (also includes correspondence as Montana Agricultural College veterinarian), 1911-1915 (Box-folder 1 / 30)
    - Dr. A.F. Baldwin (Miles City), 1921-1922 (Box-folder 1 / 31)
    - Dr. J.C. Boyd (Kalispell), 1921-1922 (Box-folder 1 / 32)
    - Dr. B.O. Fisher (Great Falls), 1921-1922 (Box-folder 1 / 33)
    - Dr. F.N. Frisch (Glasgow), 1920-1922 (Box-folder 1 / 34)
    - Dr. C.A. Hatterscheid (Glendive), 1921-1922 (Box-folder 1 / 35)
    - Dr. Warren E. Heath (Columbus), 1922 (Box-folder 1 / 36)
    - Dr. F.T. Hull (Conrad), 1922 (Box-folder 1 / 37)
    - Dr. Harry L. Jones (Drummond), 1921-1922 (Box-folder 1 / 38)
    - Dr. J.W. Kilpatrick (Hamilton), 1921-1922 (Box-folder 1 / 39)
    - Dr. A.D. Knowles (Missoula), 1921-1922 (Box-folder 1 / 40)
    - Dr. A.T. Knowles (Billings), 1921-1922 (Box-folder 1 / 41)
    - Dr. V.W. Knowles (Ronan), 1921-1922 (Box-folder 1 / 42)
    - Dr. C.F. Leslie (Kalispell), 1921-1922 (Box-folder 1 / 43)
    - Dr. Harold F. Little (Miles City) (includes letter re tuberculosis testing procedures for dairy and breeding cattle, 1923), 1921-1923 (Box-folder 2 / 1)
    - Dr. James F. Mitchell (Great Falls), 1921-1922 (Box-folder 2 / 2)
    - Dr. A.C. Morrow (Dillon), 1921-1922 (Box-folder 2 / 3)
    - Dr. E.D. Nash (Whitehall), 1921-1922 (Box-folder 2 / 4)
    - Dr. F.M. Nelson (Livingston), 1921-1922 (Box-folder 2 / 5)
    - Dr. W.C. Orr (Dillon), 1921-1922 (Box-folder 2 / 6)
    - Dr. F.B. Remer (Stanford), 1921-1922 (Box-folder 2 / 7)
    - Dr. J.W. Richardson (Malta), 1917, 1921-1922 (Box-folder 2 / 8)
    - Dr. L.P. Sharp (Moore, Harlowton), 1922 (Box-folder 2 / 9)
    - Dr. N.B. Smith (Billings), 1921-1922 (Box-folder 2 / 10)
    - Dr. C.H. Stevens (Stevensville), 1921-1922 (Box-folder 2 / 11)
    - Dr. R.C. Timmons (Havre), 1922 (Box-folder 2 / 12)
    - Dr. G.L. Utley (Twin Bridges), 1921-1923 (Box-folder 2 / 13)
    - Dr. I.W. Vinsel (Baker), 1921-1923 (Box-folder 2 / 14)
    - Dr. C.H. Wight (White Sulphur Springs), 1922 (Box-folder 2 / 15)
    - Montana Livestock Sanitary Board members, 1918-1922 (Box-folder 2 / 16)
    - Drs. D.C. Baker (Sidney), J.J. Brown (Deer Lodge), Jack Catun (Livingston), G.B. Conger (Bozeman), Gordon H. Cullison (Great Falls), S.H. Flora (Miles City), Harry E. Furgeson (Anaconda), S.D. Gates (Lewistown), K. Gerner (Stevensville), 1957-1959, 1967 (Box-folder 2 / 17)
    - Dr. G.C. Halver (Glendive), 1957-1959 (Box-folder 2 / 18)
    - Drs. Howard K. Holloway (Harlowton), James Hurry (Glendive), H.W. Jacobson (Havre), Eugene Kormendy (Missoula), Alfons Lazarewicz (Missoula), 1957-1959 (Box-folder 2 / 19)
    - Dr. Richard E. LaFrance (Bridger), 1959 (Box-folder 2 / 20)
    - T.F. Lofthouse (Missoula assistant sanitarian), 1957-1959 (Box-folder 2 / 21)
    - Drs. S.A. Lovelace (Bozeman), A.E. McChesney (Bozeman), John D. Melcher (Forsyth), J.H. Newhall (Belgrade), H.L. Nordell (Great Falls), E.M. Pruyn (Missoula), R.D. Read (Ronan), 1957-1961 (Box-folder 2 / 22)
    - Drs. W. Edwin Stahl (Missoula), E.W. Spratlin (Glasgow), I.W. Vinsel (Butte), Donald B. Wheeler (Butte), 1957-1959 (Box-folder 2 / 23)
    - Dr. J.D.C. Wipf, state sanitarian (Bozeman), 1957-1959 (Box-folder 2 / 24)
    - Dr. G.M. Wright (includes list of permittees from Powder River and Rosebud counties whose herds ranged in Custer National Forest), 1957-1959 (Box-folder 2 / 25)
    - Montana Livestock Sanitation Board members, 1957-1959 (Box-folder 2 / 26-27)
  - General Correspondence
    - Montana correspondents: A-E, 1911-1916 (Box-folder 2 / 28-30)
    - Montana correspondents: Fort Keogh Remount Station, 1911-1914 (Box-folder 2 / 31)
    - Montana correspondents: F, 1915-1916 (Box-folder 2 / 32)
    - Montana correspondents: H.C. Gardiner (Anaconda Copper Mining Company and Deer Lodge Valley Farms), 1914-1915 (Box-folder 2 / 33)
    - Montana correspondents: W.B. Gilleland (Carter County deputy sheriff), 1921-1922 (Box-folder 2 / 34)
    - Montana correspondents: G, 1911-1916 (Box-folder 2 / 35)
    - Montana correspondents: Dr. L.G. Helterine, Montana Livestock Commission stock inspector (Plains), 1921-1922 (Box-folder 2 / 36)
    - Montana correspondents: H (includes Highland Serum Company, Butte, re hog cholera serum, 1913), 1913-1917 (Box-folder 2 / 37-38)
    - Montana correspondents: A.B. Jones case (re impersonation of veterinarian), 1914-1915 (Box-folder 2 / 39)
    - Montana correspondents: Elmer Jones (Warm Springs) (re quarantine violation), 1915 (Box-folder 2 / 40)
    - Montana correspondents: I-J (includes J.W. Jones, Wibaux County sheriff), 1914-1916 (Box-folder 2 / 41)
    - Montana correspondents: Dr. M.E. Knowles, special inspector in charge of wolf and coyote inoculation (Helena), 1913-1914 (Box-folder 2 / 42)
    - Montana correspondents: K-L (includes report to J.M. Kennedy, commissioner, Bureau of Agriculture and Industry re health of livestock in Montana, 1914; also letters with Dr. W.A. Lyons re matters on Fort Belknap Indian Reservation, 1915), 1914-1916 (Box-folder 2 / 43)
    - Montana correspondents: Montana state agencies, 1911-1916 (Box-folder 2 / 44)
    - Montana correspondents: M, 1913-1916 (Box-folder 2 / 45)
    - Montana correspondents: Mc and Mac, 1914-1916 (Box-folder 2 / 46)
    - Montana correspondents: N-O (includes Oregon Short Line Railway Company stock census for cattle, milk cows, sheep, swine, horses, mules, 1913), 1913-1916 (Box-folder 2 / 47)
    - Montana correspondents: P-Q, 1913-1916 (Box-folder 3 / 1)
    - Montana correspondents: R, 1912-1916 (Box-folder 3 / 2)
    - Montana correspondents: Dr. C.E. Steinberg (Chinook), 1921-1922 (Box-folder 3 / 3)
    - Montana correspondents: S (includes resolution of thanks to Bureau of Animal Industry and Montana Livestock Sanitary Board by Montana Stockgrowers Association), 1911-1916 (Box-folder 3 / 4-6)
    - Montana correspondents: John C. Taylor (Bynum), 1921-1923 (Box-folder 3 / 7)
    - Montana correspondents: T, 1911-1916 (Box-folder 3 / 8)
    - Montana correspondents: U.S. Bureau of Animal Health local offices (correspondents include James Munro, J.O. Wilson, A.W. Miller, E.J. Cary, et al.), 1915-1916 (Box-folder 3 / 9-11)
    - Montana correspondents: United States Forest Service, 1915-1916 (Box-folder 3 / 12)
    - Montana correspondents: U-V, 1915-1916 (Box-folder 3 / 13)
    - Montana correspondents: Dr. J.R. Ward (Missoula), 1911 (Box-folder 3 / 14)
    - Montana correspondents: Dr. Howard Welch (Bozeman), 1921-1923 (Box-folder 3 / 15)
    - Montana correspondents: W, 1911-1916 (Box-folder 3 / 16-17)
    - Montana correspondents: Y-Z, 1914-1916 (Box-folder 3 / 18)
    - Out-of-state government agencies: Canada (includes letter to British Columbia Livestock Commissioner re spread of sarcoptic mange among Montana coyotes, 1915), 1914-1917 (Box-folder 3 / 19)
    - Out-of-state government agencies: Arizona, Arkansas, California, Colorado, Connecticut, District of Columbia, Georgia, 1911-1915 (Box-folder 3 / 20)
    - Out-of-state government agencies: Idaho, Illinois, 1911-1915 (Box-folder 3 / 21)
    - Out-of-state government agencies: Indiana-Iowa, 1915-1917 (Box-folder 3 / 22)
    - Out-of-state government agencies: Kansas, Kentucky, Minnesota, Missouri, 1915-1916 (Box-folder 3 / 23)
    - Out-of-state government agencies: Nebraska, Nevada, New York, North Carolina, 1913-1917 (Box-folder 3 / 24)
    - Out-of-state government agencies: North Dakota, 1911-1916 (Box-folder 3 / 25)
    - Out-of-state government agencies: Ohio, Oklahoma, Oregon, Pennsylvania (includes list of car loads of Montana cattle, hogs, and sheep received at Portland Union Stock Yards, Oregon, 1913), 1913-1917 (Box-folder 3 / 26)
    - Out-of-state government agencies: South Dakota, 1911-1916 (Box-folder 3 / 27)
    - Out-of-state government agencies: Vermont, Washington, West Virginia, Wisconsin, 1915-1917 (Box-folder 3 / 28)
    - Out-of-state government agencies: Wyoming, 1914-1916 (Box-folder 3 / 29)
    - Out-of-state government agencies: U.S. Bureau of Animal Industry (includes correspondence re Fort Belknap Indian Reservation), 1911-1915 (Box-folder 3 / 30)
    - Out-of-state government agencies: U.S. Bureau of Animal Industry (includes Veterinary Inspector Dr. H.H. Cohenour), 1915-1916 (Box-folder 3 / 31)
    - Out-of-state individuals: A-S, 1913-1916 (Box-folder 3 / 32-39)
    - Out-of-state individuals: T-V (includes foot-and-mouth, glanders, dourine, and tuberculosis statistics, 1914-1915), 1913-1916 (Box-folder 4 / 1)
    - Out-of-state individuals: W-Z, 1913-1917 (Box-folder 4 / 2)
  - General Correspondence [by topic]
    - Agricultural Research Service, 1956-1959 (Box-folder 4 / 3)
    - American Veterinary Medical Association, 1957 (Box-folder 4 / 4)
    - Anthrax, 1957-1958 (Box-folder 4 / 5)
    - Attorney General (includes information re use of tax funds to finance laboratory), 1957-1959 (Box-folder 4 / 6)
    - Bluetongue, 1956-1957 (Box-folder 4 / 7)
    - Brucellosis (includes federal interstate regulations), 1955-1960 (Box-folder 4 / 8-10)
    - Dairies (includes reports of investigations at the Montana Soldiers' Home and unlicensed dairy operations), 1956-1958 (Box-folder 4 / 11)
    - Dips, sprays, and disinfectants (includes list of approved insecticides), 1958-1959 (Box-folder 4 / 12)
    - Examiners, Board of (re Montana Livestock Sanitary Board laboratory and office facilities), 1958 (Box-folder 4 / 13)
    - Extension Service (includes Livestock Committee recommendations, Rural Progress Conference, Cascade County, and list of Home Demonstration agents), 1957-1959 (Box-folder 4 / 14)
    - Feed Lots (includes information re quarantine of R.K. Munsell feedlot, Baker; Denzel Davis feedlot, Fairfield), 1957-1959 (Box-folder 4 / 15)
    - Feeds and feeding (re use of antibiotics in feeds), 1957-1959 (Box-folder 4 / 16)
    - Foot rot, 1933, 1956-1957 (Box-folder 4 / 17)
    - Garbage-feeding (includes "Results of survey of methods of hog cholera vaccination on Montana garbage feeding premises" and lists of licensed garbage-feeding establishments), 1956-1959 (Box-folder 4 / 18)
    - Goats, 1957 (Box-folder 4 / 19)
    - Governor J. Hugo Aronson, 1958 (Box-folder 4 / 20)
    - "Grain poisonings negative diagnoses", 1945-1946 (Box-folder 4 / 21)
    - "Health, State Board of" (includes minutes of Glacier Park Sanitation meetings, list of local health officials), 1957-1959 (Box-folder 4 / 22)
    - Human food poisoning investigations (includes "Report of alleged food poisoning outbreak in St. Ignatius Public Schools"), 1956-1957 (Box-folder 4 / 23)
    - "Humans: brucellosis", 1957-1959 (Box-folder 4 / 24)
    - Interstate shipping charges (re regulation 63 "Official charges for interstate inspections"), 1951 (Box-folder 4 / 25)
    - Laboratories (re branch and state truck brucellosis laboratories), 1957 (Box-folder 4 / 26)
    - Lay inspectors (re brucellosis technicians), 1955-1957 (Box-folder 4 / 27)
    - Leptospirosis, 1956-1958 (Box-folder 4 / 28)
    - Liver flukes, 1957 (Box-folder 4 / 29)
    - Meat inspection (includes resolution of the Montana Independent Meat Packers' Association), 1958-1959 (Box-folder 4 / 30)
    - Methods of milk testing, 1951 (Box-folder 4 / 31)
    - Milk Control Board (includes materials re Ralph Hales, Conrad Creamery), 1958-1959 (Box-folder 4 / 32)
    - Milk (correspondence on antibiotics in milk), 1956-1959 (Box-folder 4 / 33)
    - Miscellaneous associations (includes Eastern Montana Hereford Association, Southeastern Montana Livestock Association, Stockmen's Disease Control Association; Western Montana Dairymen's Association; includes minutes and articles of incorporation etc.), 1957-1959 (Box-folder 4 / 34)
    - Miscellaneous diseases (includes Fish and Game investigation of disease transmitted via food in fish hatcheries), 1957-1958 (Box-folder 4 / 35)
    - Miscellaneous general correspondence, 1957-1959 (Box-folder 4 / 36)
    - Miscellaneous poisons (includes salt poisoning on John Blakenship ranch near Savage; and use of 1080 poison by U.S. Fish and Wildlife Service), 1956-1958 (Box-folder 4 / 37)
    - Miscellaneous state departments (includes list of Livestock Sanitary Board staff positions), 1958 (Box-folder 4 / 38)
    - Montana State College (contains list of members of Dairy Advisory Committee), 1959 (Box-folder 4 / 39)
    - Montana Stockgrowers' Association (includes "Some places to increase efficiency in forage and livestock production" by Forrest M. Willhite; resolutions, etc.), 1957-1959 (Box-folder 4 / 40)
    - Montana Tuberculosis Association (includes minutes), 1958 (Box-folder 4 / 41)
    - Montana Veterinary Medical Association (includes report of committee on diseases, 1940; minutes; proposed revision of constitution; bylaws; "A report to the Executive Board and Practitioners Committee"; "Report of the State Veterinarian to the 49th Annual Meeting"), 1941, 1957-1959 (Box-folder 4 / 42)
    - Montana Woolgrowers Association, 1958 (Box-folder 4 / 43)
    - Mucosal disease, 1957 (Box-folder 4 / 44)
    - National Assembly of Livestock Sanitary Officials, 1957 (Box-folder 4 / 45)
    - Public Health Service, 1957-1959 (Box-folder 4 / 46)
    - Q Fever, 1959 (Box-folder 4 / 47)
    - Quarantines, 1956-1957 (Box-folder 4 / 48)
    - Rabies: dogs, etc., 1958-1959 (Box-folder 4 / 49)
    - Redwater, 1956-1959 (Box-folder 4 / 50)
    - Regional Research Laboratory (re proposed Western Regional Animal Disease Laboratory, Bozeman), 1957-1958 (Box-folder 4 / 51)
    - Regulations (includes drafts), 1957 (Box-folder 4 / 52)
    - Rendering plants (includes lists of licensed rendering plants and materials re use of condemned meat at fish hatchery), 1957-1958 (Box-folder 4 / 53)
    - Rocky Mountain Laboratory, 1958-1959 (Box-folder 4 / 54)
    - J.W. Safford (re publication of articles and miscellaneous matters), 1956-1959 (Box-folder 4 / 55)
    - Saleyards (includes lists of Montana livestock saleyards and financial statement of Baker Sales Barn, Inc., Baker), 1957-1959 (Box-folder 4 / 56)
    - Sanitarians (includes sketch of N.L. Towne Experimental Dairy Center, Montana State College), 1957-1958 (Box-folder 4 / 57)
    - Scabies in sheep, 1957-1958 (Box-folder 4 / 58)
    - Scrapie: Wyoming outbreak (includes "Report of Scrapie Meeting at St. Louis, August 17, 1956"; and memorandum of understanding with U.S. Animal Disease Eradication Division re scrapie eradication, 1957), 1956-1959 (Box-folder 4 / 59)
    - Sheep: enzootic abortion, 1958 (Box-folder 4 / 60)
    - Sheep: miscellaneous diseases (includes parasitism and pediculosis), 1957-1959 (Box-folder 4 / 61)
    - Slaughterhouses, 1959 (Box-folder 4 / 62)
    - State-Federal responsibilities (includes diagramatic sketch of USDA-MLSB cooperative programs, maps of MLSB districts, and USDA Animal Disease Eradication Branch Montana districts), 1956 (Box-folder 4 / 63)
    - Sterility testing (includes minutes of MSLB meeting with Montana Hereford Association representatives), 1959 (Box-folder 4 / 64)
    - Tuberculosis (cattle), 1956-1958 (Box-folder 4 / 65)
    - United States Livestock Sanitary Association, 1957-1959 (Box-folder 4 / 66)
    - Vaccines and biologics, 1955-1958 (Box-folder 4 / 67)
    - Veterinarians, miscellaneous (includes material on brucellosis campaign), 1958-1959 (Box-folder 4 / 68)
    - Veterinary Research Laboratory (includes minutes of Montana Veterinary Research Laboratory Advisory Committee, 1955-1956; "Major research projects under study by the Montana Veterinary Research Laboratory", 1955-1959 (Box-folder 4 / 69)
    - Vibrosis in cattle, 1959 (Box-folder 4 / 70)
    - Water analyses (includes information re contamination of Bert and Ed Eklund ranches, Glendive, by oil drilling operation), 1956-1958 (Box-folder 4 / 71)
    - Western States Livestock Sanitary Officials (includes minutes), 1958 (Box-folder 4 / 72)
    - Wild animals, 1956-1958 (Box-folder 4 / 73)
    - Winger process for dairy products, 1953-1954 (Box-folder 4 / 74)
  - Outgoing Correspondence
    - Circular letters to deputy state veterinarians, 1913-1915, 1922-1929 (Box-folder 4 / 75)
    - Circular letters re milk plants, 1957 (Box-folder 4 / 76)
  - Miscellaneous Correspondence